<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>Tutorial - Category - Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes&#39; DevBites</title>
        <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/categories/tutorial/</link>
        <description>Tutorial - Category - Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes&#39; DevBites</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&amp;copy; 2025 Jorge D. Ortiz Fuentes</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jorgeortiz.dev/categories/tutorial/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: the not so happy path</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_not_so_happy_path/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_not_so_happy_path/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
So far, we have chosen to test things that matched our expectations of how the code was supposed to work and how the
user and the environment were supposed to behave.  But, we should also plan for the scenarios in which things don&#39;t go as
expected, and still we want our program to react properly.  We should also test for these situations and those tests are
as important as the ones that check the successful use cases.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: simplify your tests</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_simplify_tests/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_simplify_tests/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
Now that we understand the building blocks for writing unit tests in Rust, you probably feel the urge to apply that
knowledge and fully cover your application with tests.  Don&#39;t you?  Well, I would ask you to hold your horses and apply
it gradually. We still have a lot of ground to cover, but the next sections are probably going to simplify your life
right away.</p>
<p>
Again in this article, you have the final version of the <code class="verbatim">supervillain.rs</code> file at the bottom and the repo with the
incremental commits is available <a href="https://github.com/jdortiz/detestable-me-rs">here</a>.  In case of doubt, check the code or feel free to reach me through any of my
<a href="https://jorgeortiz.dev/">social media accounts</a>.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: test types</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_test_types/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_test_types/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
So you have finally learned Rust and are writing cool projects with it?  Awesome!  However, as soon as your project
starts being useful and solving some actual use cases, you realize that the quality of your code is important.  Not only
that.  The larger and more complex your project becomes, the harder it is to manually test every bit of functionality
after a change.</p>
<p>
Your first temptation might be: &#34;Why should I test everything if my changes only affect this small part of the program?&#34;
And, while in some situations that might be true, more often than not our changes affect unexpected parts of our
program.</p>]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
