<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>All Posts - Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes&#39; DevBites</title>
        <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/</link>
        <description>All Posts | Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes&#39; DevBites</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&amp;copy; 2025 Jorge D. Ortiz Fuentes</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: the not so happy path</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_not_so_happy_path/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_not_so_happy_path/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
So far, we have chosen to test things that matched our expectations of how the code was supposed to work and how the
user and the environment were supposed to behave.  But, we should also plan for the scenarios in which things don&#39;t go as
expected, and still we want our program to react properly.  We should also test for these situations and those tests are
as important as the ones that check the successful use cases.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: simplify your tests</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_simplify_tests/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_simplify_tests/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
Now that we understand the building blocks for writing unit tests in Rust, you probably feel the urge to apply that
knowledge and fully cover your application with tests.  Don&#39;t you?  Well, I would ask you to hold your horses and apply
it gradually. We still have a lot of ground to cover, but the next sections are probably going to simplify your life
right away.</p>
<p>
Again in this article, you have the final version of the <code class="verbatim">supervillain.rs</code> file at the bottom and the repo with the
incremental commits is available <a href="https://github.com/jdortiz/detestable-me-rs">here</a>.  In case of doubt, check the code or feel free to reach me through any of my
<a href="https://jorgeortiz.dev/">social media accounts</a>.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Rust unit testing: test types</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_test_types/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/rust_unit_testing_test_types/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
So you have finally learned Rust and are writing cool projects with it?  Awesome!  However, as soon as your project
starts being useful and solving some actual use cases, you realize that the quality of your code is important.  Not only
that.  The larger and more complex your project becomes, the harder it is to manually test every bit of functionality
after a change.</p>
<p>
Your first temptation might be: &#34;Why should I test everything if my changes only affect this small part of the program?&#34;
And, while in some situations that might be true, more often than not our changes affect unexpected parts of our
program.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A note about taking notes (part 3)</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_3/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_3/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
This is the last article of a series on taking notes.  In the previous ones, I shared the reasons why I think taking
notes is useful as well as some of the things that I do when I take my notes.  This article contains ways of making use
of the effort that we have put into writing those notes.  Some of them are specifically geared toward digital notes and
won&#39;t be very useful for handwritten notes, but there is one which applies only to notes on paper. 😉</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A note about taking notes (part 2)</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_2/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_2/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
This is the second article of a series on taking notes.  In the previous one, I listed my reasons for taking notes as
well as a few rules of thumb for deciding when it is worth to take a note about a topic.  In this article, I will focus
on the most practical aspects of note taking and I will share how I do it.  It shouldn&#39;t come as a shock that these
aren&#39;t the Note Commandments, but my experience and way of doing things.  I am quite happy with most of them, but there
is always room for improvement and I will be glad to hear from you and how you tackle the scenarios that I have
described here or any others that might be relevant.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A note about taking notes (part 1)</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_1/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/a_note_about_taking_notes_1/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
If you are reading this, I&#39;d bet dollars to donuts you already take notes frequently.  But, if this is not the case, I
am sorry.  Not just because you are missing a great opportunity to maximize the production of your brain, but rather
because of what you have missed so far.  But, don&#39;t worry.  It ain&#39;t late to join the club.  The sooner, the better.</p>
<p>
I must also acknowledge that this is not a comprehensive guide on note taking, but rather a series of tips that I
consider useful.  Although, I will not chicken out on sharing my reasons for taking notes, the focus will be on
describing how to get the most out of them.  I am sharing my experience here and would love to hear about yours.  Feel
free to ping me in any of the social media platforms, using the links on the home page, if you need, and let me know
other tips that have been useful to you.  I am looking forward to learning more on the topic!</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Set up and run AI Optimizer and Toolkit</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/set_up_and_run_ai_optimizer_and_toolkit/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/set_up_and_run_ai_optimizer_and_toolkit/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><div id="outline-container-headline-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="headline-1">
Intro
</h2>
<div id="outline-text-headline-1" class="outline-text-2">
<p>I have decided to create a series of pieces of content on how to use AI.  And, since there is no better tool to play
with AI than the AI Optimizer and Toolkit, I have chosen to  start by explaining how to set it up and run it.</p>
<p>
AI Optimizer and Toolkit is an Open Source project created by our team, the Microservices and AI Team.  You can use
Oracle&#39;s AI Optimizer and Toolkit to take your generative AI projects from prototype to production, independently of
their size.  Using generative AI to match your business needs is challenging and our software helps you to simplify and
accelerate the process of developing AI-based tools.  AI Optimizer and Toolkit allows you to:</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Running containers with Colima</title>
    <link>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/running_containers_with_colima/</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Jorge Ortiz-Fuentes</author>
    <guid>https://jorgeortiz.dev/posts/running_containers_with_colima/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/header-image.jpg" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div><p>
There is no better way to learn than to dive right in.  This applies to software too.  If you have ever felt tempted to
play with any of the new features of Oracle Database 23ai or to understand the advantages of the Oracle Autonomous
Database, containers can be very helpful.</p>
<div id="outline-container-headline-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="headline-1">
Goals
</h2>
<div id="outline-text-headline-1" class="outline-text-2">
<p>By the end of this article you will:</p>
<ul>
<li>Understand the pieces required to run containers in your ARM or Intel macOS system.</li>
<li>Be able to run containers for both amd64 and arm64 architectures in your Apple Silicon macOS.</li>
<li>Launch and run the Oracle Database 23ai Free Container Image or the Oracle&#39;s Autonomous Database 23ai Free Container
so you can use them locally to learn, develop or try their features.</li>
</ul>
<p>Would you prefer to watch the video? Here it is:
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share; fullscreen" loading="lazy" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y6QZqk4a_t4?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>
</p>]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
